Good. Okay. בוקר טוב Boker Tov everybody. Today's דף daf is ל"ג
Lamed Gimmel 33.
We will start again just quickly from the bottom of ל"ב עמוד
ב', Lamed Bais Amud Bais, from the beginning of the פרק, perek,
from the new משנה, mishna, and as I mentioned yesterday we are
shifting from a discussion of what situations is the נדר neder binding
to, given that one has a נדר, neder, what is included in
the נדר, neder, specifically what constitutes הנאה hana'ah benefit, because a classic
נדר neder makes something or someone forbidden in benefit. אין בין המודר
הנאה מחבירו למודר הימנו מאכל. Ein bein hamudar hana'ah mechavero lemudar heimenu
ma'achal. There's no difference between somebody, like this is from the אין
ביןs, ein bein for anybody who remembers in מגילה Megilla the list
of אין ביןs, ein bein this is one of them. So here
it would seem that there would be a large gap between somebody
who says I can't derive benefit from my friend from I can't
derive from him food. I mean that's the literal translation of the
מודר הימנו מאכל. mudar heimenu ma'achal. We'll see what the גמרא Gemara
does with that. אלא דריסת הרגל, Ela drisas ha-regel, except for like
cutting through his yard, וכלים שאין עושין בהם אוכל נפש, ve-keilim she-ein
osim bahem ochel nefesh, and borrowing vessels or objects that are not
made for the preparation of food. So if I can't get benefit
from Michael, I can't cut across his yard and I can't borrow
anything from him: his rake, his car, anything. But if I just
say I can't get from him food, I can cut across his
yard and I can borrow those types of vessels. Of course one
would imagine that there's a lot of other things I can get
from him, right, that's not food, like most things in the world
are not food, but so we'll see in the גמרא Gemara how
come it's only such a small category of difference. And then the
גמרא Gemara says המודר מאכל מחבירו, hamudar ma'achal mechavero, now if you,
I am prohibited from getting benefit from my
friend, so לא ישאילנו, lo yash'ilennu,
excuse me,
so right, so then the person who I cannot get benefit from,
Michael there, should not lend me נפה וכברה וריחים, nafah ve-kivar ve-reichayim,
a sieve and another type of a sieve and a millstone or
a mill, ותנור ve-tanur and an oven, because all those things if
I can't derive from him food, it doesn't just mean food, clearly
it means things that will lead to food or will give me
some benefit relating to food, help me make my food.
Like a plate, right? You can't.
Right. So we'll see how this is expanded in the גמרא. Gemara.
אבל משאילו חלוק וטבעת וטלית ונזמים, Aval mash'ilo chaluk ve-tabba'at ve-tallis ve-nezamim,
Michael can lend me a shirt and a ring and a cloak
and other types of rings, a nose ring. Okay, he can lend
me various types of things. Again, there's a lot of things that
fall between clothing and food preparation items that are not being addressed,
so there's also a huge gap here between what you're not allowed
to do, what you are allowed to do, there's still most things
in the universe that are not, you know, we don't know which
category they fall in here yet though.
Is there something I'm missing? It seems that the סיפא seifa is
totally redundant to the phrase וכלים שאין עושין בהם אוכל ve-keilim she-ein
osim bahem ochel unless it's a clarification. Yeah, it is a clarification.
Because it raises if it's a סיפא seifa like a separate piece.
That is true. That is true. It might be that the אין
בין ein bein line is shorter and that's from that collection over
in מגילה, Megilla, and then the then
what
this is, right, that this is a later gloss or expansion over
that terse אין בין ein bein line which is from that collection
in מגילה, Megilla, that's probably true. Okay, so now let's see what
the גמרא Gemara says. How do we make sense of this? Why
is it that so many things are forbidden if all I said
was food? So the גמרא Gemara first says the following: מאן תנא?
man tanna? Who is the author of this משנה? mishna? אמר רב
אדא בר אהבה רבי אליעזר היא.
Amar Rav Adda bar Ahava
Rabbi Eliezer hi. It's Rabbi Eliezer. דתניא, De-tanya, we learned in a
ברייתא, braita, רבי אליעזר אומר אפילו ויתור אסור במודר הנאה. Rabbi Eliezer
omer afilu vitur assur be-mudar hana'ah.
Even something that is like, that is just like waived, what's a
good translation of ויתור? vitur?
Forgiven or like not charged for. Yeah, like something that is not
charged for, like a giveaway, a freebie, is forbidden in אסור הנאה.
assur hana'ah.
Overlooked. Overlooked. All right, so if Michael here comes to my store
and normally I say like, you know, I don't know, the one
example here given is like if you buy, you know, if you
buy 12 eggs I'll give you a 13th, well what is it?
Baker's dozen, 12
loaves I'll give you a 13th roll for free. So that's something
I usually don't charge for. So if I usually don't charge for
it, he's not really getting benefit from me for that. Let's say
never. Okay, it doesn't matter. I never charge for it. Okay. Nevertheless,
even though it's not something that usually is charged for, it still
is something that he receives from me. Okay, so why? So this
is, so the better, so the more immediate example is the issue
about about דריסת הרגל. drisas ha-regel. I don't mind if people cut
through my yard, meaning I don't want everybody to start cutting through
my yard and it'll destroy my
grass, but for my neighbors, every now and then it's no problem,
it would never be anything I would charge for and so. Okay,
and nevertheless, Michael can't cut through my yard if he's not allowed
to get benefit from me. Okay, why not? So you see even
ויתור, vittur, even something that's normally like forgiving or just a freebie
or like not charged for, if you can't get benefit it doesn't
matter that there's never a dollar price assigned to it, it doesn't
matter that I usually don't mind when people do that, that still
is getting some benefit from my things. Or let's say for example
borrowing my books
or those types of things. Like okay, nobody cares. I mean, don't
take it home, but you know you pick up somebody's book, you
look through it for a few minutes, like people don't tend to
mind about that. Maybe that's a good translation, things people don't mind
about, right? Nevertheless, there's some benefit that you receive from me. So
if it's a generic you can't receive benefit, it even a type
of thing that I normally don't care about and don't mind about,
there's still something you're getting from me. Yes, Dov.
No, just you know what it's like? It's like when you're in
the שוק shuk and you buy a kilo of apples and they
throw another one in. Right. Or like when you buy flowers and
then they give an extra שפריץ. shpritz. Right. I don't know.
Is that-
Right, but those things
are- Yes, you want
to make- all right, all right. Anyway those are yes those are
all examples of that, but I do want to say that all
of those examples are a little less of a חידוש chiddush because
those are cases where anyway you're already purchasing something so then it
becomes part of what you're purchasing or
whatever and it's actually something very concrete that's being transferred. But here
we're talking even about some type of abstract
benefit that normally people don't even mind about. Sure you want to
cut through my lawn? Yeah, no problem. You take a book off
of my thing,
it's the story about the guy that comes in to דאוון daven
and he doesn't have his תפילין tefillin and he's looking around and
he finds a pair of תפילין. tefillin. He starts putting them on
and somebody says, 'Wait, you should know that those are רבינו תם
Rabbeinu Tam תפילין.' tefillin. He says, 'I'm okay, that's okay, I'm sure
he won't mind if I borrow them just for a second.' All
right.
Anyway so all right so that would be ויתור. vittur. All right.
So now the גמרא Gemara says yes, Dov.
What, he benefit, is that indirectly benefiting him?
Oh
no I think it's that you- okay, unless it's some obligation you
have to your kid so therefore if you feed your kids and
then you don't have to feed them that would be the- right,
sure. Okay let's go on. המודר מאכל מחבירו לא ישאילנו. HaMudar Ma'achal
MeChaveiro Lo Yash'ilenu.
Now we get to if you can't get food then- benefit, you
can't lend him things that are in the preparation of food and
you can't- whatever- I'm sorry, the only difference is that- like cutting
through the yard and food- things that are not used in the
preparation of food. So there's tons of other stuff that should be
allowed. So let's take a look what the גמרא Gemara says. The
גמרא Gemara says והא מי מאכל נדר? Veha Mi Ma'achal Nadar?
You only forbade food.
So why- yeah so you can access this two ways. E- A,
why is it forbidden to borrow the sieve? That's not food, right?
And B, why are- well let's start with that, right? And B,
why are a lot of other stuff- why is a lot of
other
stuff- wait okay let's start with that, that's easy enough. Why is
it forbidden to borrow the sieve? That's not food. So the גמרא
Gemara says אמר רב שמעון בן לוי Amar Rav Shimon Ben Levi
באומר הנאת מאכלך עלי. Be'omer Hana'as Ma'achalcha Alay.
You say the benefit of your food is forbidden to me, which
somehow means benefit from you that helps me relating to food. Okay,
euphemism? Well right so we'll see, the גמרא's Gemara going to work
its way through this. So the גמרא Gemara says אימא שלא ילוש
חיטין ויתן על מכתה? Eima Shelo Yalush Chittin Veyiten Al Makata?
So maybe what it means if I can't get the benefit of
your food, so that means that not just I can't eat your
food but I can't get benefit from your food. What would be
benefit from your food? I can't use it, I can't use
your cucumber to scratch my back. I can't go ahead and take
wheat and chew it and not swallow it and use it as
some type of and put it on top of a wound. Okay
so maybe it just means I can't get benefit from your food
but it doesn't- but again here borrowing your sieve is not benefit
from your food. So still how is that included? תוספות Tosafos says
that it's possible that this even means that הנאת מאכלך Hana'as Ma'achalcha
might not just mean benefit from your food but might mean food-
benefit of food.
So maybe even you can't chew my wheat so that I can
use it because somehow that's somehow benefit that you're helping create with
food. But anyway certainly it doesn't explain the sieve. So where- how
do we still get from food to things relating to the preparation
of food? So the גמרא Gemara says אימא Eima fine, read it-
I'm sorry. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רבא באומר הנאה המביאה
לידי מאכלך עלי. Amar Rava Be'omer Hana'ah HaMevi'ah Lidei Ma'achalcha Alay.
I can't get any benefit that leads to- again מאכלך ma'achalcha your
food is a little bit of a funny here, but I can't
get any benefit that brings about- I can't get anything from you
that brings about benefit- any type of food-related benefit. So therefore borrowing
from you vessels that help me in the preparation of food is
I am getting benefit from you that ultimately translates into me deriving
benefit from food. Okay? So I can't get from you something that
will lead to me getting food benefit.
Even if I want to borrow it to like catch a mouse
in the-
no that would probably be different. Okay so.
Okay, so I can't get from you food related, I can't get
from you something that will lead to food related benefit. And by
the way, that's why the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* that so many things
are forbidden, right? Because if you look at, I'm just going to
jump ahead to the next משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*, but just so we
get the full picture, look at the next משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah* a
few lines later. וכל דבר vechol davar שאין עושים בהם אוכל ochel
נפש *Vekhol davar she’ein osim bahem okhel nefesh*, things that are not
used for food, מקום שמשכירים כיוצא בהם אסור asur *Mekom shemaskirin kayoze
bahem assur*, that if they're normally rented out, it is forbidden. So
if Michael normally, if people will normally rent out their donkeys, okay,
if you ever want to use my donkey, the practice in this
town is you want to borrow your friend's donkey, that's something that
you pay for.
And then I say to Michael, Michael, can I borrow your donkey?
And he says, sure, no problem, and he doesn't charge me. That
would be forbidden even if I can't get food benefit from him,
just food benefit, why? Because that's something that normally he would charge
for. By not charging for it, he's saving me money. And by
saving me money, then that's money that I can use to buy
food. Okay, so basically... Yeah, that's true. So basically food benefit becomes
anything that is of like direct monetary benefit because that could translate
into food, and something that's not monetary benefit that people wouldn't charge
for, it can't actually give me food directly, or things that I
would somehow use in the preparation of food that would actually help
me practically get food benefit. So things that will practically give me
food or food benefit or money, direct monetary benefit, which can be
used therefore to get food. Right, even if I don't use it
but it could be used for that. Rachel, you had a question?
I'm getting lost, I feel, in details. What...
Really? In learning גמרא Gemara *Gemara* you're getting lost in details?
Yes.
Could you give me a little bit of,
a little bit of force around what is the point
of this discussion?
Sure, I mean this is if, you know, once you succeed in
making something forbidden with a vow, what are you, can you and
can you not do with that object? Or if I make you
forbidden, if I can't get benefit from you, what is the scope
of interactions that we can have? What's considered a benefit or not,
right? So in the previous פרק *Perek* we dealt with some issue
about if I can't get benefit from you, can I buy something
in your store? Is that an equal exchange? Are we both benefiting?
Is one of us the primary beneficiary, right? So here, forget a
store, we're neighbors. I got really angry at you and I took
a vow that I'm not going to get any benefit from you.
And now I need a rake to rake my lawn. Am I
allowed to borrow it or not, right, without getting my vow annulled?
Okay,
so well, if I said across the board no benefit, I can't.
If I said I won't have any, I will never get any
food benefit from you, which apparently is the thing that people said,
a lot of these things also had to do with you refuse
to come to my dinner party so I took this vow, you
know, these types of things. So there was often a food related
element to this. If I said food benefit, I can borrow your
rake because you normally never charge for your rake, so you're not
getting me any financial benefit, and it's not something that helps in
the preparation of food that leads to food benefit. But if I
said could I borrow your donkey, and a donkey is something that
you would normally rent to people and you would say, sure, go
ahead, no charge, then that's even included in the category of food
benefit because you're saving me money.
Give guidance on a practice that was common?
Or is it trying to say better really watch what you say
because it ripples far beyond?
Well, maybe both, but the primary point is as a legal discussion.
Yes.
What would be the exact words of a vow that I might
take in this case of food?
הנאת מאכלך עלי *Hana’at ma’akhalkha alai*. הנאת מאכלך עלי
*Hana’at ma’akhalkha alai*. Well, you could say קונם *Konam*, but it was
אותו קונם *Oto konam*. Right, the benefit of
your foodstuff is forbidden to me.
Okay, that's number one. Number two, wouldn't it matter what was the
reason for the vow to sort of understand everything that comes?
Yeah, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*...
yes, so if the guy beat up my
kid...
Right, so that's like the previous פרק *Perek*. So that's the whole
previous פרק *Perek* is you look at the reasons and the context
and the motivation to understand did the person really mean it, is
it really binding, or under what circumstances is it binding? That's what
I said. This פרק *Perek* now shifts and says you meant it,
it's binding, now we just have to understand what the scope of
it is. Okay. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues.
אמר רב פפא *Amar Rav Pappa*, שק לבי פירות *Sak lavei peirot*,
what's, the types of objects that are included in food related benefit
are not only things that are used for the preparation of food
included in our משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*, but even things that are used
for the transportation of food.
Right, a sack to bring fruit וחמור להביא עליו פירות *vekhamor lehavi
alav peirot*, or a donkey... so I was using my donkey example,
here we see that a donkey... a shopping cart right, a shopping
cart right, right, so here we see a donkey is forbidden. Now
the question is, I would say getting back to Michael's point, the
זו is important here. If I say can I borrow your sack
and I'm going to use his sack to be transporting I don't
know my clothes, my foods, my kids are going to camp and
I'm packing up all their all their clothes in that, that would
be okay and I want to use his duffle bag for that.
If I want to use your donkey because I want to go
on a hike or something, that would be okay. But if I'm
using it for the purpose of transporting food, then that is included
in food-related benefit. פירות ואפילו צנא בעלמא peirot va'afilu tzana be'alma even
a basket. Okay. הנאה המביאה לידי מאכל hana'ah hamevia lidei ma'achal who
that is considered benefit that brings about that like leads to food-related
benefit. שאל רב פפא sha'al Rav Pappa Rav Pappa asked. סוס לרכוב
עליו sus lirkov alav how about a horse to ride on, right,
so you don't וטבעת לראות בה vetaba'at lera'ot bah
or a signet ring that I can sort of show you know
like like show off with, right, מהו mahu what's the story? מפסע
ומיזל בארמיה mifsaya umizal be'armaya or how about cutting through your yard?
So now what are the issues about this? So here, the primary
difference is, this is not about getting the food to me or
preparing the food, this is getting me to the food. Okay, so
the last example is maybe the easiest. Can I cut through your
yard? Okay, somebody's having a barbecue in the next yard over, can
I cut through your yard to get to the barbecue? Is that
הנאה המביאה לידי מאכל? hana'ah hamevia lidei ma'achal? Okay, yes it does
sort of help me get food benefit, but it's not sort of
directly getting the thing from you know it's not object-related as much
it is me related or it's not anyway directly about the food
as directly about the food itself, it's getting me to the food.
That is the cutting through the yard. Now how about the horse?
So you could say I'm I want to ride on your horse
to get to also to get because you know can I borrow
your car? I'm invited out to a dinner. Can I borrow your
car to get to the dinner? Okay, all that makes sense. The
signet ring is a little bit more bizarre, but the ראשונים Rishonim
say you know if I'm going to a to a to a
meal
and I come dressed in clothes that make me look really important
and חשוב chashuv they're going to offer me you know they're going
to seat me in the better section, they're going to give me
the better food. Okay, so therefore because of the clothes that you
lend me, ultimately I will get a nicer meal and better food.
So is that included? It's not directly relating to the object of
the food, but it does help me in food matters. So מאי
mai what's the story? So the גמרא Gemara says like this, תא
שמע Ta shema come and hear, אבל מושאל לו חלוק וטלית נזמים
וטבעות aval mush'al lo chaluk vetalit nezamim vetaba'ot the end of the
משנה Mishnah says you can lend him all these clothes. So היכי
דמי heichi dami what's the case? אילימא שלא לראות בהן eilima shelo
lera'ot bahen if the purpose is not to like appear important with
these clothes, it's just סתם stam I need to borrow some clothes.
צריכא למימר tzricha lemeimar of course you can lend it to me.
That's not something that's food related. צריכא למימר tzricha lemeimar right, אלא
לאו אפילו לראות בהן ela lav afilu lera'ot bahen the משנה mishna
seems presumably means even if those clothes are important for me to
look important and would help me with food issues, nevertheless it's permissible.
ותני מושאל לו vetani mush'al lo you can lend it to him.
גמרא Gemara says לא לעולם שלא לראות lo leolam shelo lera'ot no,
no, לעולם leolam שלא לראות shelo lera'ot it's not talking in that
special case that you want to look important. ואיידי דתנא רישא לא
ישאילנו ve'aidi detana reisha lo yash'ilenu since the beginning said don't lend
him you know things like the הסיב hasiv and whatever, so תנא
סיפא מושאל לו tana seifa mush'al lo it says these things you
can lend him, but it's not telling you such a really big
חידוש. chiddush. So we really don't know the answer about benefits that
sort of help me get to the food or help me appear
in a certain way, whether that is included or not.
That was actually unsatisfying.
Okay, yeah, some random items into the סיפא seifa of the משנה.
mishna But if I want to borrow your tie because I'm going
out you know dinner with my wife, right, I'm not going to
get any more food as a result.
Right, unless they have a policy that no tie no service.
Right, exactly, exactly. That's why exactly and that's the point you made
before, the ל lamed here is important. Like if there are some
things that have a whole range of possible use, then it depends
it matters the context. Okay, so now the next משנה mishna. which
I sort of mentioned before because the next משנה Mishnah. helps us
explain why there are not more differences between generic הנאה hana'ah and
food הנאה hana'ah because anything that can translate into money is also
a food הנאה. hana'ah. ובכל דבר שאין עושין בו אוכל נפש uvechol
davar she'ein osin bo ochel nefesh objects that are not used for
food, מקום שמשכירין כיוצא בהן makom shemashkirin kiyotze bahen if these types
of things are rented out, then אסור assur it's forbidden because then
you would act because then it would be considered a what a
monetary benefit. You didn't charge me the money and therefore that's money
that you I put in my pocket that could translate into food.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, מכלל michlal now by the
way, I do wonder what the category of מקום שמשכירין כיוצא בהן.
makom shemashkirin kiyotze bahen. Can I borrow your car, right? So that's
something that you know if you don't have a car to borrow,
you gotta go to a rental agency and rent a car. But
it's often friends will often like rent you know I don't know
anyway you know you need my car for a few hours fine
no problem, right? So what does משכירין כיוצא בהן mashkirin kiyotze bahen
mean? Does it mean like neighbor- on a personal basis people rent
it to their you know to to people they know personally, or
that when you know or that this object object when it's not
available, things that people rent when they can't get it elsewhere? Right?
So I mean I could understand that even in this case
where you would have no problem lending me my car, your car,
that would be אסור because if you say I'm sorry, I'm using
my car, I'd love to lend it to you but I can't,
I'm using it, I actually am going to go ahead
and rent one from Enterprise or whatever, right? So therefore if you
say no problem use it, I'm not using it, you essentially saved
me money. Because if I couldn't find a friend to lend me
their car, I would have had to shell out money from my
pocket. Do you understand my point? Even if it's not something that
your friend would normally rent you, you didn't do me any favor
by saying sure, borrow my car, I won't charge you for it.
It wouldn't be a הוי אמינא hava amina you would ever charge
me for it. But nevertheless, the fact that you are lending it
to me has saved me from the need to go to the
rental agency and to rent one.
Is the car also equally likely to rent?
That's an interesting question. I don't know, that's why I'm raising this
issue.
All these examples are agricultural or food-related. Is it possible in this
short משנה Mishnah. that you just read about the שכירה, sechira, they're
pushing the limits to the meaning of מאכל ma'achal and אוכל to
be like it's consumer? In other words, it's a consumer model, right?
In other words, the money in a way is the substitute for
the food. Do you understand what I'm saying?
They're trying to expand beyond food.
Yeah, but it doesn't include things that are consumed that aren't money
or food, if
I wanted to use your water to shower with, that wouldn't be
a problem. So I don't think it's just about consumption, but it
is true this high emphasis on food. Look, the thing that I
was thinking about mentioning is, there's a discussion in the גמרא Gemara
that every time the תורה Torah says לא יאכל, lo yochel, does
it include all איסור הנאה, issur hana'ah, all forms of benefit? And
exactly, and the one explanation that is given there by רש"י, Rashi,
why does לא יאכל lo yochel don't eat as the presume to
understand all benefit as רש"י Rashi says? Well, because normally any types
of benefits ultimately what do you do
with other things that you would normally be monetary benefit and so
on, you probably translate it into food. You probably buy food. Food
is seen as the most staple type of a thing, so it's
more all-encompassing.
But yeah, so that definitely is interesting, right? Like one would imagine
if I said another type of a statement, הנאה המביאה לידי, hana'ah
hamevia lidei, I don't know, comfort or I don't know what else
I would say, it might not be as inclusive. There's something about
food that's assumed to be inclusive.
Well it's definitely going on the food, right? Because there's a ו,
vov, so it's conjunctive, right? Isn't it the continuation of the previous
משנה Mishnah, mostly?
וכל
דבר
שאין עושין בו אוכל נפש.
she'ein osin bo
ochel nefesh.
Dov is just asking why the idea of food is all of
a sudden really and very expansive ways. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says מכלל דרישא אף על פי שאין משכירין, michlal de-reisha af al
pi she'ein maskirin, so in the beginning when it deals with things
like borrowing your sieve or whatever, that's even if it's not rented.
So מאן תנא הוא, man tanna hu, who said that? That benefit
that people normally don't charge for and that people just sort of
say sure, no problem, go ahead and borrow my sieve, or my
millstone, even so that's considered benefit even though it's something people don't
charge for? So who is that? אמר רבה בר בר חנה רבי
אליעזר, Amar Rabba bar bar Chana Rebbe Eliezer, like we said before
it's רבי אליעזר. Rebbe Eliezer. Okay, but in a way, it's funny
because here it's like a little less relevant because who cares whether
you charge for it or not? It's exactly stuff that leads to
food-related benefit. But maybe still that's the point, who cares if you're
getting benefit from me, if it's not a benefit that people normally
care about, maybe it doesn't constitute הלכתית halachically benefit. So what we're
saying is even if people normally don't mind and don't care about
it, it constitutes benefit. If you say no benefit from me, that
includes everything, anything, anything you would get from me, even things that
people don't care about like cutting through my yard. And if you
say food benefit, then it's specifically about either things that translate into
money, that have saved you money, so I lent you my car
so you don't have to rent it from someone else, or things
that directly or indirectly are related to the eating or preparation of
food. So now the next
משנה. Mishnah המודר הנאה מחברו, Hamudar hana'ah mechaveiro, so now we move
away from that food thing, which I admit is a little confusing.
המודר הנאה מחברו, Hamudar hana'ah mechaveiro, somebody says that they are prevented
from getting benefit from their friend, שוקל את שקלו, shokel et shiklo,
so Michael cannot get הנאה hana'ah from me. Either I took the
vow, Michael doesn't really matter. But I can pay Michael's שקל shekel
to the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So if you ask me, that's
a pretty big הנאה. hana'ah. If Michael can't get הנאה hana'ah from
me, I can still pay his shekel dues. It's a pretty big
הנאה. hana'ah. Why can I do that? Not only that, ופורע את
חובו, uporea et chovo, Michael owes somebody a million dollars, I can
pay off his debts.
So that's not הנאה, hana'ah, I don't know what is. ומחזיר לו
את אבידתו. umachzir lo et aveidato. The third one makes of course
the most sense. If I find Michael's wallet, I can return it
to him because then I have a מצוה mitzvah to return it
to him and ultimately I'm giving you something that is yours. The
fact that I'm doing a service for you,
I'm obligated to do that type of a service.
What would be the assumption that if I return your wallet I'm
getting some kind of הנאה hana'ah from that act even though הנאה
hana'ah derived from you?
You if you if you return my my wallet maybe I got
הנאה hana'ah from you? You get I'm so grateful.
No no. מודר הנאה מחבירו. mudar hana'ah mechavaro. I can't get any...
I can't get הנאה hana'ah from you, so
the חוזר chozer can be שוקל את שקלו. shokel es shiklo. It's
it's all a little confusing to keep track of who's who here.
But ראובן Reuven can't get הנאה hana'ah from שמעון, Shimon, שמעון Shimon
can still pay ראובן Reuven's HIR-J dues right, there's no one has
paid in 30 years anyway. He can pay his debts and he
can return his lost object, return his אבידה. aveidah.
All of that
is not considered that ראובן Reuven is getting
הנאה hana'ah from שמעון, Shimon, which is pretty bizarre. Who's doing the
talking, ראובן? Reuven? Who made the vow doesn't matter. Doesn't matter. But
ראובן Reuven can't get benefit from שמעון, Shimon, so שמעון Shimon can
still do all these things
for ראובן.
Reuven. מקום שנתנו עליה שכר, makom she-notnu aleha sechar, now if normally
you would pay the person who returned your lost object for their
not directly for their service because you're not allowed to, but at
least for the time that they took off from their normal work
in order to find and return the object, so תיפול הנאה להקדש,
tipol hana'ah le-hekdesh, then that הנאה hana'ah goes to הקדש. hekdesh. Now
why does that הנאה hana'ah go to הקדש? hekdesh? דוב Dov returned
my lost object, I'm not allowed to get benefit from him, but
I didn't get benefit from him, it's not called benefit. I want
to give him 20 bucks for his efforts, okay, why does that
have to go to הקדש? hekdesh? Like like give the money to
צדקה. tzedakah. He's allowed to get benefit from me, okay, so why
does it have to go to הקדש? hekdesh? So we will see
that you know we'll see that the
so the case is because what דוב Dov says is no no
no I did it you don't have to pay me forget it
keep your 20 bucks. So now I'm in a bind, right, because
I wanted to give him the 20 bucks, he tells me to
keep it. So if he's telling me to keep it, now am
I getting 20 bucks from him and am I getting הנאה hana'ah
from him? So in the case where he doesn't want the money
that I want to pay him, then I give it to צדקה
tzedakah or else then I will be getting הנאה hana'ah from him.
If he didn't want it you
just pay him.
But I was the one that was אסור בהנאה assur be-hana'ah and
you still were able to return my wallet.
Well you were confusing it. I'm having you returning my wallet. You're
returning my wallet. Okay. So then I want that's okay that's not
considered I'm getting I'm not getting benefit from you, it's my wallet.
I want to give you 20 bucks for your effort and you
say, which would be okay, because then you say no no no
keep it it's fine. So I can't keep it now because now
I'm getting something from you. So now I have to give the
money to צדקה. tzedakah.
So you you're telling me that according to the הוה אמינא havamina
here is that if you lose your wallet and I return it
there's no הנאה hana'ah there because it was yours anyway?
Yes, that's what that's what I'm saying.
I don't understand the first example.
I know the whole thing is counterintuitive. Yes.
Well then why do I learn something?
What? Well we'll see what the גמרא Gemara says, but that first
of all, Rachel, you think that everything has meaning.
Some things some things are just you have to know what the
law is, right? It would be nice to okay I mean that
could be a second order question, but let's first understand. The first
purpose is to determine the law, the second purpose is now what
deeper meaning can we find here? Okay. In other words...
So
now I'm trying to get the structure too.
Okay. Here's ראובן, Reuven, here's
שמעון, Shimon, okay. Okay,
and now
he cannot get הנאה hana'ah from him, okay. He cannot get any
הנאה hana'ah from שמעון. Shimon. Even though he can't get any הנאה
hana'ah from שמעון, Shimon, שמעון Shimon can go ahead and pay his
pay
ראובן Reuven's
שקל, shekel, right,
there's no one has paid in 30 years anyway.
He can pay his debts
and he can return his lost object, return his אבידה. aveidah. All
of that is not considered that ראובן Reuven is getting הנאה hana'ah
from שמעון, Shimon, which is pretty bizarre. Now returning the אבידה, aveidah,
well I'm just giving him back his own thing. Now you could
say he got a service but, you know, but in terms of
the actual
thing that he put in his pocket he only put his own
thing and maybe because שמעון Shimon was had a מצוה mitzvah to
return it so it's not really... So this is the easiest one
to understand, then ראובן Reuven says let me give you 20 bucks
and he says no no no keep it, so then ראובן Reuven
can't keep the 20 bucks he gives it he has to give
it to הקדש, hekdesh, he has to give it to צדקה. tzedakah.
But here he's really getting ראובן Reuven alleviate you know he's he's
getting ראובן Reuven out of some serious debt, you would think that
that's a real benefit. Okay, but that money is going to some
third party, right? So here is the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash or
the creditor. The money is going to a third party, but ראובן
Reuven is actually is actually
being freed from the debt. Now that would seem to be a
pretty big benefit but it's not going directly to him. So that's
the point of the משנה. Mishnah In one case he gets something
but he gets his own. In one case he doesn't physically get
something... Even though he gets freed from debt. So it's a very
narrow definition of הנאה hana'ah, *Hana'ah* that allows this to happen.
This really clarifies הנאה *Hana'ah* now, right? If I have an obligation
to a creditor, good,
that's a clear explanation, not a deeper meaning.
Yes, but if I fulfill my obligation to a creditor, yes, that's
not הנאה *Hana'ah*, that's the fulfillment of obligation.
Yes, I don't know, if you're saddled with debt, I don't know,
if you ever did a net worth, you've got your assets and
your what's the other thing? Liabilities, right. So now we've taken the
thing like a million dollars off of the liabilities column and we're
telling you that's not real הנאה *Hana'ah* because the money didn't go
straight to me.
No, but you know why?
My net worth now shot up a million dollars.
I might feel elated. I might feel alleviated.
That's just you feel alleviated, your net worth has now increased significantly,
right? I mean, it's still bizarre, but because there was not some
direct money that came straight to me.
No, no, but...
I don't care how you feel.
No, that's not what I'm saying. That's not what I'm saying. If
I owe you money, right,
and
I pay you, or someone else pays... someone else pays you. Right.
Okay. So... so... I'm... I'm...
I've... I'm at a zero point, in other words, I've been...
You just did not directly receive any.
All I... all I... all what was... all what was done was
my obligation as a human being. There wasn't a...
No, there was, well the גמרא Gemara *Gmara* is going to make
it that, but that's not all that was done. All that was
done was that your financial obligation in a real debt was erased
from your, you know, from your column. There was a very, very
concrete financial gain that you received, except you received it indirectly. Okay.
And that seems to be the point. The point is not that
there wasn't a gain, but that it was an... it was seen
to be indirect. Yes.
So שמעון Shimon *Shimon* is allowed to pay ראובן Reuven. *Reuven*'s creditor.
Right. שמעון *Shimon* allowed to pay a debt that someone owes to
ראובן *Reuven*?
Somebody owes, pay
ראובן *Reuven* money that somebody else owes him?
No, because that would be direct benefit that ראובן *Reuven*... I mean
because you would say it's not benefit, oh you mean it's sort
of like the אבידה *Avedah*, because he's got the money coming anyway.
That's an interesting question. So that would make a...
right, I understand, I understand your point. It's like, is that like
a מחזיר אבידה *Machzir Avedah*? That money was coming to me anyway,
except rather than getting, you know, David here to pay me the
money, you paid me the money. In the end, I got... that's
an interesting question. No, I hear, I don't know, it's a good
question. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
You basically want to say that that could be like a מחזיר
אבידה *Machzir Avedah*. It was money I was getting anyway, you just
helped me get it. Right. It's interesting. All right, so the...
there's a... there's a מצווה *Mitzvah* here.
Yes. Well, that's... that's מחזיר אבידה *Machzir Avedah* is definitely that, right.
Okay.
So it's a חיוב
*Chiyuv*, it's like a מצווה *Mitzvah*. All right, so now the גמרא
Gemara *Gmara* says like this: אלמא *Alma*, so here's how the גמרא
Gemara *Gmara* conceptualizes, conceptualizes these two cases. אלמא *Alma*, says the גמרא
*Gmara*, what you see is: אברוחי ארי בעלמא הוא *Avruchei Ari Be'alma
Hu*, that we consider paying off somebody's debt just a scaring away
a lion. ושרי *Veshari*, it's permissible. Because here are these creditors, or,
and they were, they're about to come and like a lion, like
attack me, and you prevent them from attacking me. So you didn't
actually give me something, you just stopped some external thing from taking
something away from me. Okay. So, which of course, the problem with
that is, is that the lion metaphor is something that's like, it's
like something that's, you know, undeserved, unwarranted, wrong, right? Here there was
a reality that I actually took at least in the creditor, I
took these people's, this person's money. Right, so it's funny to call
that like a lion. Anyway, but that's how it's being perceived. I
would have more used a model of גרמא *Grama*, you're only indirectly...
anyway, you're stopping something bad, you're not directly giving me something good.
So the גמרא *Gmara* says, right, so the גמרא *Gmara* says, מאן
תנא
*Man Tana*, who is this תנא *Tana*?
So the גמרא *Gmara* says, אמר רבי אושעיא *Amar Rabbi Oshaya*, says
רבי אושעיא *Rabbi Oshaya*, זו דברי *Zu Divrei*, right, זו דברי חנן
Chanan *Zu Divrei Chanan*, these are the words of חנן Chanan? *Chanan*.
So we'll see in a minute who חנן Chanan *Chanan* is, that
gets us back to discussion in כתובות Ketubot *Kesuvos*. But what I'll
tell you now, חנן Chanan *Chanan* is the story that somebody left
and went on a business trip and he did not make any,
any accommodations for his wife, and he has an obligation to pay
for his wife's food there, and here his wife has... can't put
any food on the table. So what I do is I basically
go ahead and give his wife some money so she can go
to the supermarket and buy some food, and then the guy comes
back and I say, could you please reimburse me? Because I was
paying, you know, gave your wife let your wife money, and he
said, nope, I don't want to reimburse you. So חנן Chanan *Chanan*
said, well, I'm out, I'm out all the money, I was such
a צדיק tzadik *Tzadik* and I'm out all that money, because basically
the wife is a creditor, she, money is owed to her, the
guy isn't around, I am paying off this guy's creditor. creditors, okay?
And since I did not make any explicit stipulation with him that
he would have to reimburse me and I was just paying off
his creditors, then I cannot demand anything from him. So you see
that חנן Chanan's is of the opinion that paying off the creditors
is not considered like I actually gave anything to that person that
I'm entitled to any reimbursement. So here too, paying off creditors is
not like שמעון is giving anything to ראובן. So רבא אמר, Rava
amar, now רבא Rava says, אפילו תימא דברי הכל, afillu teima divrei
hakol, it even is the Rabbis who disagree with חנן Chanan's and
say that I can get reimbursement in that case. דבמודר הנאה, debemudar
hana'ah, the case here is a special case. דיהיב על מנת שלא
לפרוע. deyihiv al menat shelo lifro'a.
So it wants to make this what דוב Dov wanted to make
it. דוב Dov wanted to say in this case, this creditor, he
lent me money but he was very nice. He said, 'You know
what דוב, Dov, such a good guy that here's,
here's $10,000. If you can pay me up, it's okay. If you,
you know, if you get the money and if you get the
money back then I want you to reimburse me, but if you
can't put the money together, it's all right, you don't have to
worry about it in the end, okay?' So it's a loan because
I'm not going to ever demand it, you know, I can't sort
of sue you for it in בית דין, beit din, but you
still owe me the money. But now it becomes an issue where
you owe it to me as דוב Dov was saying of a
personal obligation, right, but not as anything that ever is really can
trans-, you know, that dollars and cents I can actually force you
to pay. So in that case what you did to me by
paying this guy off was you helped me out in a personal
way, maybe you saved me from some embarrassment, but you never actually
gave me any, it would never have been in my liabilities column
of my net worth because it was never something I ever would
have been ever ever forced to pay. So he makes it into
a special case which is not obviously פשט pshat of the משנה.
mishnah Okay, so now the גמרא continues.
Yes?
Is there possibility to release myself from the נדר neder retro-, I
mean like in the past?
Yes, yes, that's other discussion we had before and we're going to
have again. But the answer is yes. But now we're dealing with
when you haven't done that. All righty, take care. So the גמרא
says like this, so okay. מאי חנן, mai Chanan, who is
חנן? Chanan, דתנן במשינה, detnan bemishinah, מי שהלך למדינת הים mi shehalach
lemedinat hayam ועמד אחד ופרנס את אשתו. ve'amad echad upernes et ishto.
חנן אמר איבד את מעותיו. Chanan amar ibbad et me'otav. So
the guy who paid for my wife's food, he wasted his money
because he was צדיק but he can't collect it back from me
that he didn't make any stipulation with me, so he just paid
off a creditor. נחלקו עליו בני כהנים גדולים, nechlaku alav benei kohanim
gedolim,
so the children of the כהנים גדולים, kohanim gedolim, interesting that they
were a class, argued with him. ואמרו, ve'amru, no, ישבע כמה הוציא
ויטול, yishava kamma hotzi veyitol, that
the person who paid for my wife can take a שבועה shevu'ah
how much money he spent and he can collect it from me.
Okay, so there's that question about whether מבריח ארי, mavriach ari, somebody
who's paying off a creditor is considered like somebody who was actually
doing benefit for me or not. So now the גמרא says, and
there's some discussion that the ר"ן Ran and earlier גמרות gemarot get
into that that sort of explained the case of the debt, how
the case of the debt could be a case where you don't
really have to pay, but how is the case of the שקל
shekel a case where you really don't have to pay? And it
has certain scenarios where maybe you actually are, have already paid your
שקל shekel to the בית המקדש beit hamikdash but it got lost
and the normal practice would be to repay it but you don't
really technically have to repay it. Wants to try to translate that
into somewhat of a parallel case. Yes Charlie?
Haven't we had this case before?
Yes, this case has come up, it came up in כתובות and
I think it might have even come up earlier here. So the
גמרא tends to do that you know, sometimes have similar discussions or
quote משניות mishnayot or whatever in other places. Okay so now the
גמרא says like this, אמר רבי דוסא בן הרכינס כדבריהם. amar Rabbi
Dosa ben Horkinas kedivreihem. So רבי דוסא בן הרכינס Rabbi Dosa ben
Horkinas said like the בני כהנים גדולים benei kohanim gedolim
that you do not have to, that you do have to pay.
אמר רבי יוחנן בן זכאי יפה אמר חנן. amar Rabbi Yochanan ben
Zakkai yafeh amar Chanan. No, חנן Chanan is right. הניח מעותיו על
קרן הצבי. henniach me'otav al keren hatzvi. You, it's like you put
your money on the horn of a deer. So like you just
flush your money down a toilet. Which is not, you know, if
you didn't make any explicit stipulation, so you did this guy a
favor but you didn't actually give him anything. And since it's not
seen as you concretely gave him something, he does not owe you
anything, and here too it would not be forbidden by a case
of איסור הנאה. issur hana'ah.
רבא לא אמר כרב הושעיא, Rava lo amar keRav Hoshaya, רבא Rava
did not say like רב הושעיא, Rav Hoshaya, it's only חנן our
משנה, mishnah. דקמוקים לה למתניתין כדברי הכל, dekamokim lah lematnitin kedivrei hakol,
he'd rather have our משנה go like everybody, right? רב הושעיא לא
אמר כרבא, Rav Hoshaya lo amar keRava, רב הושעיא Rav Hoshaya
didn't say it was like רבא Rava that it was everybody,
because A, you would have just had to say a weird אוקימתא
okimta of our משנה that it's a special case where it's a
loan that didn't really have to be paid, and number two, גזירה
שלא לפרוע משום לפרוע, gezerah shelo lifro'a mishum lifro'a,
because
he would say look, even if according to the Rabbis that argue
on חנן that say that paying off a creditor is real benefit?
So if that's true, if you're not allowed to get benefit from
your friend, A, he certainly couldn't pay off creditors you really have
to pay the money to, that's real benefit. But B, the rabbis
would logically say you couldn't even pay off a creditor that said
you wouldn't have to pay him back. Because if we let the
guy pay off creditors that you don't have to pay back, which
is a bizarre category, how often does that happen, right? Then he'll
come to allowing him to pay off creditors he really does have
to pay back. Okay, so got it, so the משנה says that
Shimon can pay off my creditors. Why? So the simple explanation רב
אושעיא Rav Oshaya said is, this is חנן's idea. חנן's idea is
מבריח ארי, mavriach ari, you're getting rid of somebody who's coming to
take stuff away from me, but you're not giving me anything directly
and therefore it's not considered benefit. That's clearly פשט pshat of the
משנה. רבה Rava makes it a special case. No, no, no, it's
a special case where I really didn't have to pay the creditor
if I never got together the money. So therefore you Shimon didn't
really do me any favors. And therefore everybody would agree that's okay.
And רב אושעיא Rav Oshaya says back that no, in that case
if really we're not dealing with חנן, if it really is considered
benefit paying off a creditor, then I wouldn't let the guy pay
a creditor that even you didn't have to pay back because then
it would just lead to allowing him to paying back creditors that
you really did owe the money to. All right, clearly the פשט
pshat is like רב אושעיא Rav Oshaya here that this is the
position of חנן that it's not considered to be a benefit, which
is an amazing חידוש, chiddush, but again that's the surprising, that's the
deeper meaning of these משניות mishnayot to show you the exact parameters
of what is and is not included. So on the one hand
when you say food, food somehow means this big category, but when
you say הנאה, which should mean, which should obviously include cases like
this, we're saying it doesn't, that's not direct, that's only indirect. Okay,
now מחזיר לו אבדתו. machazir lo avedato.
So that's these cases. Now we get to returning the object, which
is again just giving me back something that is my own. So
now we have to let's take a look at that. פליגי בה
רב אמי ורב אסי. pligi ba Rav Ami v'Rav Assi. So רב
אמי Rav Ami and רב אסי Rav Assi debated this. חד אמר
לא שנו אלא שבנכסי מחזיר אסורין על בעל אבדה. Chad amar lo
shanu ela b'she-nichsei machazir asurin al ba'al avedah. Okay,
it's only true that you can return my lost object if your
property is forbidden to
me, דכי מהדר ליה, d'chi mahadar lei, מידעם דנפשיה קמהדר ליה. midam
d'nafshei ka-mahadar lei.
You're just returning to me something that's my own. אבל נכסי בעל
אבדה אסורין על מחזיר, Aval nichsei ba'al avedah asurin al machazir,
but here's ironically, so if I can't get benefit from Shimon, he
can return my object. But let's say Shimon can't get benefit from
me. Do you think he could return my object? What would you
think? If Shimon can't get benefit from me, of course he can,
he's only giving me something. Of course, why is that a problem?
So here's the irony. If Shimon can't get benefit from me, אבל
נכסי אבדה אסורין על מחזיר, aval nichsei avedah asurin al machazir, לא
קמהדר ליה. lo ka-mahadar lei. He can't give me my lost object.
Why? Listen to this. דקמהני ליה פרוטה דרב יוסף. de-ka-mahanei lei prutah
d'Rav Yosef. Because he is getting benefit. If Shimon returns Reuven's lost
object, Shimon's getting benefit from Reuven. You know what benefit he's getting
from Reuven? That he does not have to pay the פרוטה דרב
יוסף. prutah d'Rav Yosef. What is the פרוטה דרב יוסף? prutah d'Rav
Yosef? So there's a debate in the גמרא in בבא מציעא. Bava
Metzia. If I find Rachel's object here, I've found Rachel's iPhone, and
I am going to and I have to now return it to
her. And an עני ani comes to me, Charlie comes knocking at
my door, and he's collecting money for עניים, aniyim, for for a,
you know, הכנסת כלה, hachnasas kallah, okay, and I get to say,
can I say to Charlie, or I can say to Charlie, Charlie
I'm sorry, you know, I can't give you any money, I'm in
the middle of doing a מצוה mitzvah of returning Rachel's lost object,
and עוסק במצוה פטור מן המצוה. osek b'mitzvah patur min ha-mitzvah. So
I get to ignore people that are asking for צדקה tzedakah if
I'm in the middle of returning a lost object. And I get
to save myself the dollar I would have had to give to
the שנורר, schnorrer, if I was, sorry, to the to the
עני ani if I, okay, we'll have to edit that out, if
I was
in the middle of the 10,000
people just, I know, if I was in the middle of now,
now, therefore, therefore here's the question. That would be if Charlie would
actually come asking for asking for the for a dollar. Okay, he
didn't come asking for a dollar. I'm returning Rachel's object. What is
my relationship to this object if some damage occurs to it? Am
I a שומר חנם? shomer chinam? I'm watching it for free, nobody's
paying me. Or am I a שומר שכר? shomer sachar? I am
watching it for a fee and therefore I have a higher level
of liability. And רב יוסף Rav Yosef says, so of course we
would all say שומר חנם. shomer chinam. רב יוסף Rav Yosef says
I am a שומר שכר. shomer sachar. You know why? I do
get paid for it. The way what I get paid for is,
I get freed from any עני ani that comes and asks me
for money since if that were ever happen while I was in
the process of returning it, I'd get some benefit and therefore I'm
a שומר שכר.
shomer
sachar. Oh, so it's a
world, it's like
we live in a matrix of
potential מצוה mitzvah obligation.
Now it has to be a מצוה *mitzvah* that would cost me
money, because מצוות *mitzvos* that wouldn't cost me money, like is not
considered הנאה *hana'ah*, right? Whatever. מצוות לאו להנות ניתנו *Mitzvos lav lehanos
nitnu*. Anyway, anyway, I don't know if that's related. Anyway.
Or if you're returning this ערב סוכות *erev Succos*, you don't have
a לולב *lulav* yet.
Right, or something like that. Now, that's in terms of what type
of a שומר *shomer* I'm considered. That's... the גמרא *Gemara* says what
type of a שומר *shomer* I'm considered to be. Now the question
is can we use this idea? This was the idea of רב
יוסף *Rav Yosef* who said this, that I'm a שומר שכר *shomer
sachar* because I don't have to... everybody agrees that I don't have
to give the עני *ani* the dollar. But רב יוסף *Rav Yosef*
said because of that possibility, you're going to be a שומר שכר
*shomer sachar*. So that gets called the פרוטה *prutah* of רב יוסף
*Rav Yosef*, the dollar of רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* that the returner
of an אבידה *aveidah*, that is seen as a concrete benefit the
returner of an אבידה *aveidah* gets. So now, I would return this
object to Rachel, and I, however, was really upset, we had a
fight, and I took a vow that I can't get any הנאה
*hana'ah* from Rachel. So can I return her object? In the process
of returning her object, I'm getting הנאה *hana'ah* from her. You know
what הנאה *hana'ah* I'm getting from her is that I don't have
to give money to the עני *ani* that comes to me. Now,
that's if this, paying off a creditor is indirect and that's allowed,
even though you just paid off a million dollar loan. But now,
right, because since in the process of doing a מצוה *mitzvah*, I
mean, one could even say I'm not doing the מצוה *mitzvah* for
Rachel, I'm doing the מצוה *mitzvah* for God. That's the... that's why
I'm פטור *patur* for the עני *ani*, but somehow because I'm involved
in Rachel's object and I'm doing the מצוה *mitzvah* and I'm going
and I'm trying to find Rachel to return it, that's like I'm
getting הנאה *hana'ah* from her that it's saving me from having to
pay these עניים *aniyim*. So that is the question of can I?
Let's just read it. So the first opinion is I can't return
the object to the person I can't get benefit from, because I'm
getting this benefit, the פרוטה *prutah* of רב יוסף *Rav Yosef*. וחד
אמר אפילו נכסי בעל אבידה אסורין על המחזיר מהדר ליה *Vechad amar
afilu nichsei baal aveida asurin al hamachzir mahadar lei*. No, even if
I can't get benefit from Rachel, I can return her lost object.
ומשום פרוטה דרב יוסף לא שכיח *Umishum pruta deRav Yosef lo shechiach*.
The likelihood that an עני *ani* will come while I'm in the
process of returning the אבידה *aveidah* and I'll get it, that is
not a common scenario and therefore the act of returning the אבידה
*aveidah* is not considered an act by which I derive benefit from
Rachel. Okay, and therefore if it happens that an עני *ani* came
and I saved money, fine, but in principle, I don't have to
worry about that and I'm allowed to go ahead and do it
and it's not considered an act of deriving benefit. Yes, Charlie. Wait,
Charlie had something. Yes.
Is there really a מצוה *mitzvah* חיוב *chiyuv* to give to every
single עני *ani* who asks you?
Well, no, but we won't talk... I mean, it depends on what
the circumstances are. But so what, in a circumstance where there is
a מצוה *mitzvah*?
Could he ask somebody else to return the אבידה *aveidah* to the
owner?
Yeah, I could do that. I could hand it off to somebody.
Okay, so we will develop this tomorrow. I'll see you all, or
hopefully, I'll see you all tomorrow. Oh, actually I won't. שבת שלום
*Shabbat Shalom* because I just forgot I'm not going to be here.